Guide to the South Africa Documentary Photographs Collection, 1940s-2007 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Beyond the Barricades Series, 1981-1988, (2 boxes)
  - Omar Badsha, 1981-1987, (15 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs, 12x16 gelatin silver prints, document South African political organizations and individuals: the ANC Women's League, the United Democratic Front (UDF), Inkatha, and Chief Buthelezi. They depict protests, strikes, police confronting activists, and other events under apartheid..
  - Julian Cobbing, 1986, (2 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs document protest by the ANC and the UDF.
  - Gille de Vlieg, 1984-1986, (5 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs include FEDTRAW protest, police violence, and a speech by Archbishop Desmond Tutu.
  - Paul Grendon, 1985, (1 print) (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts a funeral following a police shooting.
  - Dave Hartman, 1985-1986, (4 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs depict protest and UNC and UDF funerals.
  - Steve Hilton-Barber, 1986-1987, (2 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs depict the Port Elizabeth Youth Congress, funerals, and protest.
  - Rashid Lombard, 1985, (1 print) (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts a United Women's Organization protest.
  - Roger Meintjies, 1987, (2 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs depict ANC and UDF protest.
  - Gideon Mendel, 1985-1987, (13 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs depict UDF protests, funerals, police and right-wing violence, and other events of protest and violence under apartheid.
  - Eric Miller, 1986-1987, (3 prints) (Box 1)
    Photographs depict the National Union of Mine Workers and COSATU events.
  - Santu Mofokeng, 1987, (1 print) (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts mourning for the death of an ANC member.
  - Themba Nkosi, 1985, (1 print) (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts police and the body of a protester.
  - Cedric Nunn, 1986-1988, (2 prints) (Box 2)
    Photographs depict Inkatha.
  - Billy Paddock, 1986-1987, (3 prints) (Box 2)
    Photographs depict funerals and Pondo/Zulu violence.
  - Myron Peters, 1984, (1 print) (Box 2)
    Photograph depicts the Natal Indian Congress.
  - Chris Qwazi, 1986, (1 print) (Box 2)
    Photograph captures police and funeral mourners.
  - Jeeva Rajgopaul, 1986, (1 print) (Box 2)
    Photograph depicts a labor strike.
  - Guy Tillim, 1986, (3 prints) (Box 2)
    Photographs represent a funeral, a rally, and vigilante violence.
  - Subeida Vallie, 1985, (1 print) (Box 2)
    Photograph of a funeral.
  - Paul Weinberg, 1980-1987, (14 prints) (Box 2)
    Photographs document the UDF, the ANC, the Leandra Youth Congress, the Food and Allied Workers Union, and other groups under apartheid.
  - Unidentified, (6 prints) (Box 2)
    Photographs depict protest, families, a jazz event, and portrayals of everyday life.
- The Cordoned Heart Series, 1979-1984 and undated, (15 boxes)
  The Cordoned Heart Series is a collection of 191 matted and unmatted gelatin silver prints of images taken by South African photographers and dating from between 1979 and 1984. Also contains digital versions of the images and textual materials from the exhibit "South Africa: The Cordoned Heart," curated by Alex Harris, Margaret Sartor, and Cornell Capa. The images derive from the Cordoned Heart exhibit, which appeared originally at the International Center of Photography in 1986 and toured for a number of years afterwards. The Cordoned Heart exhibit was the culmination of a documentary project by the photographic collective Afrapix, as part of the Second Carnegie Inquiry into Poverty and Development in South Africa. An accompanying book, South Africa: The Cordoned Heart (1986), was edited in part by Afrapix member Omar Badsha.
  The series documents a crucial period of protest and social upheaval in South African history, focusing on poverty and the daily lives of people living under apartheid. Photographs depict neighborhoods, rural and urban residences, social life, families, work conditions, events in South African history such as forced relocations, and scenes of political or labor conflict.
  Twenty photographers are represented: Paul Alberts, Joseph Alphers, Omar Badsha, Michael Barry, Bee Berman, Michael Davies, David Goldblatt, Paul Konings, Lesley Lawson, Chris Ledechowski, Rashid Lombard, Ben Maclennan, Jimi Matthews, Gideon Mendel, Cedric Nunn, Myron Peters, Berney Perez, Jeeva Rajgopaul, Wendy Schwegmann, and Paul Weinberg. Textual materials include exhibit brochures and an exhibit installation guide. There is also a limited edition portfolio with ten signed photographs selected from the exhibit. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images mounted on the library server; please contact a reference archivist for access.
  The Cordoned Heart Series is physically arranged by size of prints and matting. In some cases, prints grouped by size and mat size have variable window sizes. Photographs are arranged in the finding aid by photographers, listed alphabetically. Textual materials are placed at the end of the series; materials for the Cordoned Heart portfolio are with the original photographs rather than the portfolio prints.
  All matted prints except the ten Cordoned Heart portfolio prints show dates and captions. The portfolio prints are captioned in the accompanying text. Unmatted prints are not dated or captioned, but dates and captions for some are listed in the textual materials at the end of the series, based on the book The Cordoned Heart.
  - Paul Alberts, 1979-1982 and undated
    Images depict scenes from Capetown and rural areas with subjects such as unemployed men, children playing, families, and women cooking.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (12 prints) (Box 3)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (6 prints) (Box 5)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 6)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 15)
  - Joseph Alphers, 1983 and undated
    Images show unemployed and working men as well as soccer and other activities in rural areas.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (6 prints) (Box 3)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 12)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 15)
  - Omar Badsha, 1981-1983 and undated
    Photographs depict daily life of unemployed men, pensioners, people at home, people plastering a house, a funeral, street scenes, and township scenes; also included are religous events, protest meetings and march, and a pension payout. Some images were shot in urban and rural Lesoto.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (11 prints) (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (4 prints) (Box 6)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (4 prints) (Box 7)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (5 prints) (Box 14)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (3 prints) (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (3 prints) (Box 15)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 16)
  - Michael Barry, 1980 and undated
    Portraits and scenes from Haven Night Shelter make up this grouping of images by Barry.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 7)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 16)
  - Bee Berman, undated
    Images depict a municipal compound and a religious event.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (3 prints) (Box 3)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 16)
  - Michael Davies, undated
    Contains images of children at an amusement park.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (4 prints) (Box 3)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 8)
  - David Goldblatt, undated
    Photographs depict bus commuters, a woman protesting on the street, and Desmond Tutu speaking at a funeral.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (7 prints) (Box 3)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 16)
  - Paul Konings, 1980
    Konings' images capture scenes from migrant labor camps.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 3)
  - Lesley Lawson, 1984
    Images are portraits of a man and child from a rural settlement and of cleaners.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (5 prints) (Box 3)
  - Chris Ledechowski, 1983 and undated
    Photographs show Crossroads squatter camp, temporary shelters, and agricultural scenes.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (7 prints) (Box 3)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 13)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 16)
  - Rashid Lombard, undated
    Images were taken at a political demonstration.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 3)
  - Ben Maclennan, 1980-1982 and undated
    Photographs document migrant work life, depicting scenes at a gold mine hostel, people being removed to other lands, trucking, and a mine workers' compound. Other images show rural scenes, socializing, and families.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (5 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (7 prints) (Box 9)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 13)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 16)
  - Jimi Matthews, undated
    Photograph of a man shearing a sheep.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, (1 print) (Box 4)
  - Gideon Mendel, 1984 and undated
    Images show a rural family, women, children, and an old man.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (4 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 9)
  - Cedric Nunn, 1983 and undated
    Nunn's photographs capture scenes at an industrial park and a woman indoors.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (3 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 10)
  - Berney Perez, undated
    Images feature a funeral, a body on the street, and a woman outdoors.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (4 prints) (Box 4)
  - Myron Peters, 1984
    Images include events and daily life such as a political meeting and men selling carpets.
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 10)
  - Jeeva Rajgopaul, 1983 and undated
    Images show women gardeners and portraits of men. 11x14 prints were sent from Rajgopaul to the Duke Center for Documentary Studies, separately from the Cordoned Heart exhibition.
    - 11x14 gelatin silver prints, (10 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 prints, (1 print) (Box 10)
  - Wendy Schwegmann, 1983-1984 and undated
    Images capture life in the rural areas, focusing on schoolrooms, landscapes, men, women, and children. Other images show forced removals, a funeral, a vigil with Desmund Tutu, women voting, and former gang members.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (10 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (5 prints) (Box 10)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 13)
  - Paul Weinberg, 1984 and undated
    Images taken by Weinberg include portraits and scenes depicting farm workers, union meetings, prison labor, strikes.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (7 prints) (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (6 prints) (Box 11)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (1 print) (Box 13)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (5 prints) (Box 14)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, (2 prints) (Box 16)
  - Unidentified photographers, undated
    These six prints by unidentified photographers depict farmworkers, an election, and rural landscapes in South Africa.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, (6 prints) (Box 4)
  - Textual Materials, circa 1986-1991 and undated
    - Cordoned Heart exhibit description and installation materials (Box 17)
- Then and Now Series, 1963-2006, (16 boxes)
  Consists of 160 prints documenting South Africa before and after apartheid. The series originated in a 2008 exhibition at Duke University curated by South African photographer Paul Weinberg, and includes the work of eight South African photographers: David Goldblatt, George Hallett, Eric Miller, Cedric Nunn, Guy Tillim, Paul Weinberg, Graeme Williams, and Gisèle Wulfsohn. The exhibition featured twenty photographs from each photographer: ten photographs taken during apartheid, and ten taken during the period following democratic elections in 1994. All of the images are available in an online exhibit. The series also contains a digitized audio file recorded at the exhibition's opening, also available through the online exhibit.
  Arranged alphabetically by photographer. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images mounted on the library server; please contact a reference archivist for access.
  - David Goldblatt (Box 18-19)
    Goldblatt's images show National Party supporters, landscapes, and life in rural and urban South Africa.
  - George Hallett (Box 20-21)
    Includes photographs of Cape Town's District Six before its destruction under apartheid, two women meeting Nelson Mandela, scenes from urban life, and depictions of religious ceremonies in Johannesburg and Cape Town from 1994 to 2004.
  - Eric Miller (Box 22-23)
    Images depict protests, arrests, police and military operations, as well as images from a mental hospital, everyday life, and religious ceremonies and street festivals.
  - Cedric Nunn (Box 24-25)
    Collection includes portraits of men, women and families, a funeral, weddings, and life in post-apartheid Johannesburg.
  - Guy Tillim (Box 26-27)
    Includes photographs depicting rival groups fighting for control of a settlement in Cape Town in 1986, life in Transkei, an election rally, and urban life in Johannesburg.
  - Paul Weinberg (Box 28-29)
    Images depict life in 1980s Johannesburg, protests, rural life, outdoor scenes, and political rallies.
  - Graeme Williams (Box 30-31)
    Images depict a crowd clashing with police, a protester killed during a march, a clinic, and life in Cape Town and Johannesburg in 1997-2005.
  - Gisèle Wulfsohn (Box 32-33)
    Includes images of an election polling station, children in Durban and Pretoria, urban life in Johannesburg, and portraits of men, women and children, including people afflicted with HIV and AIDS.
  - Exhibit Opening, audio file, (120 MB) (Box 32-33)
    Audio mp3 file recording the opening event for the Then and Now exhibit at Duke University. The file has been mounted to the library server; please consult with a reference archivist for access.
- Underexposed Series, 1940s-2007 and undated, (17 boxes)
  These images originated from a project of the Centre for Curating the Archive at the University of Cape Town to collect the work of South African documentary photographers considered relatively unknown and "underexposed" at the time. Photographs feature a variety of subjects, including South African political protests, family life, leisure pursuits, rural and impoverished social conditions, and working conditions. Eleven photographers are included: Rodney Barnett, Arthur Bolton, Basil Breakey, Anne Fischer, Jenny Gordon, David Hemson, Daniel Morolong (some of whose work was created in the earliest years), Cedric Nunn, Graeme Williams, Janje Wissema, and Gisèle Wulfsohn.
  The series houses over 600 photographic prints, including both color and black-and-white images. There are approximately 50 digital prints from each photographer, as well as a smaller number of gelatin silver prints. Digital prints are 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints on Epson Archival Matte Paper. Prints were distributed to both the Centre for Curating the Archive in Cape Town and Duke University's Archive of Documentary Arts.
  Prints are grouped by photographer. The gelatin silver prints of one photographer, Graeme Williams, are arranged in five topical subseries, and appear first. All other photographers are arranged in alphabetical order. All measurements are in inches unless otherwise noted. Graeme Williams images are available on the library server; please contact a reference archivist for assistance.
  - Graeme Williams, (103 prints)
    Arranged by subseries, with titles assigned by the photographer. There are five topical subseries arranged in alphabetical order, consisting of 8x10 inch black-and-white gelatin silver prints: Hard Ground, Hlabisa AIDS Orphans, Interplay, Sacred Heart House, and Two Dogs. In addition, there is a subseries of 8x10 color prints and 5x7 inch reference prints entitled The Edge of Town.
    - The Edge of Town, undated, (70 prints) (Box 34, 34-A)
      The subseries consists of 22 5x7 inch and 48 8x10 inch color reference prints. Images often resemble collages, with the camera capturing individuals and street scenes framed alongside public artwork and street advertisements and signs. Box of 8x10 prints includes an essay on the project and a CD-ROM with image files.
    - Hard Ground, 2003, (22 prints) (Box 35)
      Consists of 8.25x8.5 inch color portraits of mine workers individually or in groups, posed in their working environment. The images were commissioned by the University of Cape Town for an exhibit in the university's Chemical Engineering Building.
    - Hlabisa AIDS Orphans, circa 2001, (19 prints) (Box 36)
      Prints are 8x10 inch gelatin silver; the images were taken in Hlabisa, KwaZulu-Natal. The bulk are portraits of children at home or outside.
    - Interplay, 1989-circa 1997, (18 prints) (Box 37)
      These 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints portray the recreation and family life of members of a Johannesburg group household that included photographer Graeme Williams. Subjects include outdoor recreation, parents and children, nudes, and scenes of life at home. A list of captions taken from the photographer's website is housed with the photographs.
    - Sacred Heart House, circa 1991, (11 prints) (Box 38)
      8x10 inch gelatin silver depicting staff and patients at a Catholic AIDS hospice in Kensington, Johannesburg.
    - Two Dogs, 1999-2000, (11 prints) (Box 39)
      A series of 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints of two black dogs playing on a beach at Pringle Bay near Cape Town.
  - Rodney Barnett, (49 prints)
    The subseries covers a variety of themes and geographic locations, some outside South Africa.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 40)
  - Arthur Bolton, (38 prints)
    The bulk consists of formal portraits of men, women, and children in African dress; some are studio portraits and some are posed in outdoor settings.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 41)
  - Basil Breakey, (47 prints)
    Photographs in the subseries show jazz musicians, bands, audiences, instruments, and other jazz-related themes.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 42)
  - Anne Fischer, (52 prints)
    Themes include scenes of rural village life and portraiture.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 43)
  - Jenny Gordon, (58 prints)
    Arranged by subseries, with titles assigned by the photographer. There are three topical subseries: Breathing Spaces, Mai Mai Project, and Johannesburg Portraits.
    - Breathing Spaces: Environmental Portraits of Durban's Industrial South, 2002-2007, (19 prints) (Box 44)
      The subseries consists of portraits of men, women and children primarily at home in Merewent, Durhan.
    - Mai Mai Project, (19 prints) (Box 44)
      Consists of portraits of men and women in and around a migrant worker hostel in Johannesburg.
    - Johannesburg Portraits, 1980s, (20 prints) (Box 44)
      Portraits in Hillbrow and other Johannesburg inner city suburbs. Subjects are primarily portrayed at home.
  - David Hemson, (46 prints)
    Hemson's images center on political protests, especially anti-apartheid marches. There are also photographs of industrial settings and workers.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 45)
  - Daniel Morolong, 1940s-1960s, (48 prints)
    Photographs depict posed groups or informally gathered groups of South Africans, especially at social events at clubs and other locations. There are many photographs of Morolong's family at home, at the beach, and elsewhere.
    - Color and black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 46)
  - Cedric Nunn, (60 prints)
    The bulk of the Cedric Nunn photographs feature scenes and portraits taken in rural South Africa and impoverished urban areas, depicting rural villages, urban street scenes, and inhabitants.
    - Color and black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 47)
    - 8x10, 12x16, and 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints (Box 48)
  - Jansje Wissema, (51 prints)
    Chiefly portraits of children and adults on the street and at home.
    - Black-and-white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 49)
  - Gisèle Wuhfsohn, (50 prints)
    Chiefly portraits of women. Includes portraits of women political activists such as Amina Cachalia, Thandi Modise, and Ray Alexander Simons. There are also scenes of families and friends at home or at play.
    - Color and black and white 11.7x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 50)